Guide to the Tom Davis Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Tom Davis papers
1966-2012
GEN MSS 1523
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
60
(57 containers)
The collection comprises the papers of comedian and writer Tom Davis. Davis was best known for being one-half of the comedy duo Franken & Davis, with comedian, writer, and former United States Senator Al Franken, and for their work as writers and performers on the television program, Saturday Night Live. Materials in the collection document Davis' life and work, and include scripts, episode rundowns, and other materials related to Saturday Night Live; writings by Davis, including movie screenplays and drafts of his memoir, 39 Years of Short-Term Memory Loss; correspondence; photographs; clippings; audiovisual materials; and ephemera.
Davis, Tom, 1952-2012
Aykroyd, Dan
Franken, Al, 1951-
Garcia, Jerry
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises the papers of comedian and writer Tom Davis. Davis was best known for being one-half of the comedy duo Franken & Davis, with comedian, writer, and former United States Senator Al Franken, and for their work as writers and performers on the television program, Saturday Night Live. Materials in the collection document Davis' life and work, and include scripts, episode rundowns, and other materials related to Saturday Night Live; writings by Davis, including movie screenplays and drafts of his memoir, 39 Years of Short-Term Memory Loss; correspondence; photographs; clippings; audiovisual materials; and ephemera.
Arrangement
Organized in five series: I. Saturday Night Live, 1975-2011; II. Film Projects, 1977-2008; III. Writings, 1977-2012; IV. Personal Papers, 1966-2012; V. Audiovisual Materials, 1977-2009.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, Inc. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Tom Davis (1952-2012) was an American writer and comedian, best known for his comedy writing partnership with Al Franken and their work on the television program, Saturday Night Live (SNL). He was born Thomas James Davis on August 13, 1952 in St. Paul, Minnesota, where he grew up and befriended Franken while both were students at the Blake School in Minneapolis. After graduation, Franken went to college at Harvard University, while Davis attended the University of the Pacific in Stockton, California. Davis withdrew from college after a year and returned to the Twin Cities area to pursue a career in comedy. After Franken graduated from Harvard, the two moved to Los Angeles, California to perform stand-up comedy, and were discovered by SNL creator Lorne Michaels, who hired them as two of the show's first writers. Notably, Franken and Davis were offered a single apprentice job as a duo by the writer's union and were paid a single salary. Their writing credits for SNL were subsequently attributed to "Franken & Davis."
Davis worked for SNL from 1975 to 1980, and again from 1986 to 1994. During his tenure on the show, Davis created or co-created many notable sketches, including "Theodoric of Yorik, Medieval Barber," "Nick the Lounge Singer," "The Continental," and "Coneheads." In addition to his writing work for SNL, Davis wrote many screenplays for films, including the 1993 film, Coneheads. He also wrote several screenplays for films that were never produced, including an adaptation of the Kurt Vonnegut novel, The Sirens of Titan (co-written with Grateful Dead member, Jerry Garcia), and a third installment of the original Ghostbusters film series (co-written with Dan Aykroyd). In 2009, Davis published his memoir, Thirty-Nine Years of Short-Term Memory Loss, and in 2012 he co-authored the book Owsley and Me: My LSD Family with Rhoney Gissen. The latter book chronicled the life of Grateful Dead sound engineer, Owsley "Bear" Stanley and his role in the 1960s counterculture in San Francisco, California.
In 2009, Davis was diagnosed with throat and neck cancer and died on July 19, 2012 at age 59. He was survived by his wife, Mimi Raleigh, whom he married in 1991.
Comedians -- United States -- 20th Century; Television writers -- United States -- 20th Century; Screenwriters -- United States -- 20th Century; Screenplays; Television scripts; Saturday night live (Television program); Vonnegut, Kurt, 1922-2007
- Saturday Night Live, 1975-2011; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents Tom Davis' career as a writer for the television program, Saturday Night Live, as well as his comedy writing partnership with Al Franken, as the duo Franken & Davis. Materials include scripts and rundowns of full episodes of the program; scripts for individual sketches written by Franken and Davis; a grouping of unsorted and unidentified skripts; audiovisual materials; and other related papers, including notes, correspondence, and employment contracts.
  - Scripts and rundowns of full episodes
    - Season 2, 1976-1977, undated; 19 folders (Box 1)
    - Season 3, 1977-1978, undated; 24 folders (Box 2)
    - Season 4, 1978-1979, undated; 15 folders (Box 3)
    - Season 4, 1978-1979, undated; 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Season 5, 1979-1980, undated; 9 folders (Box 4)
    - Season 5, 1979-1980, undated; 12 folders (Box 5)
    - Season 16, 1990-1991, undated; 19 folders (Box 6)
    - Season 17, 1991-1992, undated; 13 folders (Box 7)
    - Special episodes
      - Paul Simon Special, 1977, undated; 1 folder (Box 8)
      - Bob and Ray, Jane, Laraine & Gilda, 1978-1979, undated; 8 folders (Box 8)
      - Steve Martin's Best Show Ever, 1981, undated; 1 folder (Box 8)
      - Gilda Radner - Live From New York, undated; 1 folder (Box 8)
      - Grateful Dead, Radio City, undated; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Scripts of individual sketches
    - "Alcohol and Its Effects", 1975, undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Apartment Scene", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Asbestos Squad", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Birdie Cola", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Bulgaria This Winter", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Coneheads", 1983, undated; 11 folders (Box 9)
    - "Cufflinks of the Gods", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Defense Department", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "The Dick Nixon Show", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Don Pardo's Screen Test", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Ford Delegate", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Ford Pyschiatrist", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Gentle Man", 1975, undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "H&L Brock", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "How to Entertain a Gay", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Mc Mac", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Jeopardy 1999", undated; 1 folder (Box 9)
    - "Johnny Ralston", 1975; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "JFK Medallion", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Larraine/Don't Know", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Mr. USA", 1975; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Nebraska Pimp", 1976; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Nessen Opening", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "New Zealand Lamb Dish", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Nosh 'N Wash", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Olympic Runners", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Operating Rooms", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Pity Thy Neighbors", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Placenta Helper", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Pong", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Securiton, Security Guard", 1975; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Steve Gannon", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Update", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Wake up with Frank", 1978; 1 folder (Box 10)
    - "Warthogs", undated; 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Unsorted scripts
    - Unsorted scripts, 1975-1978, undated; 14 folders (Box 10)
    - Unsorted scripts, 1975-1976, undated; 21 folders (Box 11)
    - Unsorted scripts, 1978-1980, undated; 10 folders (Box 12)
    - Unsorted scripts, 1978-1980, undated; 11 folders (Box 13)
    - Unsorted scripts, 1979-2011, undated; 15 folders (Box 14)
    - Unsorted scripts, undated; 23 folders (Box 15)
    - Unsorted scripts, 1987-1990, undated; 20 folders (Box 16)
    - Unsorted scripts, 1977-2003, undated; 14 folders (Box 17)
  - Audiovisual materials
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - SNL - Kevin Bacon, 1991 February 9; 1 DVD-R (Box 51)
    - SNL, undated; 1 DVD-R (Box 51)
    - The Franken & Davis Show "The White House Los Angeles Part 2", 1977 August 5; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002137181492)
      Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - "Lungbrush", 1991 October 21; 1; 00:02:06; The program has a time code burned into the lower third of the picture. There are video tracking errors when the bars are up. It clears up when the video is in black prior to the program beginning. (Box 52, Item barcode 39002104618278)
    - "Push Button to Cross Street", undated; 1 (Box 53)
    - "Push Button to Cross Street", undated; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 53)
    - "Bogus Prod. 'Cat Dentist' 10/15/87", 1987 October 15; 1; 00:04:24; Video clipping as recorded. (Box 53, Item barcode 39002104618286)
    - "Atomic Lobsters", circa 1978
      - Atomic Lobster video transfer (memo), 1978; 1 folder (Box 55)
      - Lobster A, track 2, circa 1978; 1 (Box 55)
      - Lobster 1(A), circa 1978; 2 (Box 55)
      - Lobster B, circa 1978; 2 (Box 55)
      - Lobster 1(B), circa 1978; 2 (Box 55)
    - Planet of the Men vs. Planet of the Women, undated; 1 (Box 56)
    - SNL Time Square Opening with F and D MOS [Man on the Street], 1978 February 24; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002137181526)
  - Other papers
    - Franken & Davis employment contract with NBC, 1975; 1 folder (Box 13)
    - Tom Davis employment contract with NBC, 1989; 1 folder (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, 1980, undated; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1980, undated; 11 folders (Box 18)
    - Correspondence regarding the sketch, "First He Cries", undated; 1 folder (Box 18)
    - Notebooks, undated; 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Notes, 1977, undated; 1 folder (Box 18)
    - Notes, 1978-1980, undated; 7 folders (Box 13)
- Film Projects, 1977-2008; Series II
  Materials in this sereis document film projects that Tom Davis worked on throughout his professional career, and consist primarily of screenplays. Of note are screenplay drafts for the 1993 film Coneheads, which was based on the Saturday Night Live sktech of the same name; screenplay drafts of an unproduced adaptation of the Kurt Vonnegut novel, Sirens of Titan, co-written with Grateful Dead lead singer Jerry Garcia; and screenplay drafts for an unproduced third installment of the original Ghostbusters film series, co-written with Dan Akroyd.
  - Coneheads
    - Drafts, 1992-1993, undated; 15 folders (Box 19)
    - Drafts, 1992-1993, undated; 11 folders (Box 20)
    - Drafts, 1992-1993, undated; 36 folders (Box 21)
  - Ghostbusters III
    - Drafts, 1997-2008, undated; 6 folders (Box 21)
  - Hitting the Wall
    Also identified under the working title Hell in a Bucket.
    - Correspondence, 1996-2004, undated; 36 folders (Box 22)
    - Drafts, 1996-2004, undated; 17 folders (Box 22)
    - Drafts, 1999-2005, undated; 27 folders (Box 23)
    - Drafts, 1996-2000, undated; 11 folders (Box 24)
    - Drafts, 1999-2002, undated; 17 folders (Box 25)
  - Saturday Night Live Movie
    - Drafts, 5 folders (Box 26)
  - Sirens of Titan
    - Drafts, 1987-1989, undated; 13 folders (Box 26)
    - Drafts, undated; 4 folders (Box 27)
  - Son of Liberty
    Also identified under the working title Copper Mountain.
    - Drafts, 2000-2002, undated; 14 folders (Box 27)
    - Drafts, 2000-2002, undated; 14 folders (Box 28)
    - Research files, 2000-2002, undated; 6 folders (Box 28)
    - Research materials, undated (Box 29)
  - Other film projects
    - Awkward and Clumsy, 1996; 1 folder (Box 28)
      Written by Dan Aykroyd and Tom Davis.
    - Bacchus is Back, 2005; 1 folder (Box 28)
    - Behind the Curve, 2002, undated; 1 folder (Box 28)
    - Date Night, 1984; 1989; 2 folders (Box 28)
      Written by Al Franken and Tom Davis.
    - Mars Base One, 1988-1989, undated; 6 folders (Box 28)
      Written by Dan Aykroyd, Tom Davis, Susan Beavers, Stuart Kreisman, and Chris Cluess.
    - Nightmare in Bonarco, undated; 5 folders (Box 30)
    - Nineteen Eighty-Five, 1981-1982, undated; 3 folders (Box 30)
      Written by Tom Davis, James Downey, and Al Franken.
    - Nineteen Ninety-Four, 1981, undated; 3 folders (Box 30)
    - The Trillionaire, 2005–2006; 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Unnamed Tesla film project, undated; 1 folder (Box 30)
    - Unidentified film project, 1997, undated; 1 folder (Box 30)
- Writings, 1977-2012; Series III
  Materials in this series primarily consist of drafts of Tom Davis' published memoir, 39 Years of Short-Term Memory Loss. Also included are an assortment or other writings, chiefly one-off scripts for television and radio shows.
  - 39 Years of Short-Term Memory Loss (Memoir)
    - Drafts, 2007-2008, undated; 7 folders (Box 31)
    - Drafts, 2006-2008, undated; 25 folders (Box 32)
    - Drafts, 2004-2005, undated; 39 folders (Box 33)
    - Drafts, 2008-2012, undated; 36 folders (Box 34)
    - Drafts, 2004-2009, undated; 2009; 34 folders (Box 35)
    - Drafts, 2004-2009, undated; 32 folders (Box 36)
    - "39 Years - photos for book per Tom", 2008 November 23; 1 (Box 51)
  - Other Writings
    - Al Franken Show, undated; 3 folders (Box 37)
    - Al Franken Show
      - Franken Show, 2006 June 9; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002137181476)
      - Tom Davis on the Al Franken Show, 2004 October 13; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002137181484)
    - Car Talk, 2001-2003, undated; 3 folders (Box 37)
    - "The Dark Side of Death", 2010, undated; 2 folders (Box 37)
    - Franken and Davis Show, "Holocaust", 1980 February 13; 1 folder (Box 37)
    - "Ice Out", 2012, undated; 4 folders (Box 37)
    - The International Radio & Television Society, undated; 1 folder (Box 37)
    - Mad About You, "Old Money", 1995 May 14; 1 folder (Box 37)
    - "The New Show", 1983-1984, undated; 16 folders (Box 38)
    - Roseanne, "Thing in the Wall", undated; 1 folder (Box 37)
    - Symposium, 2000, undated; 6 folders (Box 37)
    - Symposium (d. 2), 2000 September 19; 1 (Box 51)
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - The Tom Davis Project, 2005, undated; 3 folders (Box 37)
    - Trailer Park, Series II, Shoot II, 1997; 1 folder (Box 37)
      Single manuscript including scripts for episodes in following order: 18, 27, 30, 26, 28, 20, 24, 25, and 29.
    - Wrap Around the World, 1988 September 10; 1 folder (Box 37)
    - Tom Davis interviews Chris Hurit and his father, 2008; 1 folder (Box 39)
    - Scot and Evelyn interviewed by Tom Davis, undated; 1 folder (Box 39)
    - Tom Davis interviews Dick and Dena, undated; 1 folder (Box 39)
    - Howard Frisch Obituary, 2007; 1 folder (Box 39)
    - Manhattan Serenede, undated; 1 folder (Box 39)
- Personal Papers, 1966-2012; Series IV
  This series includes an array of materials related to Tom Davis' personal life, including correspondence, notebooks, photographs, posters, and ephemera. Of particular note are a signed plaque from Steve Martin to Tom Davis, thanking Davis for his contribution to "Steve Martin's Best Show Ever"; a signed typewritten letter to Franken and Davis from Mitzi Shore, owner of the Comedy Store club in Los Angeles; and a collection of original concert posters, most promoted by Bill Graham, for concerts by the Grateful Dead, Jimi Hendrix, Jefferson Airplane, and others.
  - Correspondence, 1998-2010, undated; 22 folders (Box 40)
  - Awards, 1986–2006; 4 folders (Box 40)
  - Notebooks, 1992-1996, undated; 29 folders (Box 41)
  - Notebooks, undated; 18 folders (Box 42)
  - Notebooks, 2006, undated; 11 folders (Box 43)
  - Drawings, 2009, undated; 6 folders (Box 43)
  - Photographs, undated; 8 folders (Box 43)
  - Articles/clippings, 1984-2011, undated; 25 folders (Box 43)
  - Articles related to Tom Davis' death, 2012; 20 folders (Box 44)
  - Received film scripts, correspondence, notes, ephemera, 1984-2011, undated; 11 folders (Box 45)
  - Correspondence, notes, ephemera, clippings, 1996-2010, undated; 29 folders (Box 45)
  - Unsorted papers and ephemera, 1988-2012, undated; 12 folders (Box 46)
  - Open letter to Franken and Davis from Mitzi Shore, 1977 (Box 47)
  - Signed Plaque from Steve Martin, 1981 (Box 47)
  - Calendar, clippings, printed ephemera, 1983, 2006, undated; 3 folders (Box 47)
  - Franken and Davis performance posters, 2006, undated; 3 folders (Box 48 (Oversize))
  - Concert posters, circa 1966-1970; 27 folders (Box 48 (Oversize))
  - Concert posters, circa 1966-1970; 30 folders (Box 49 (Oversize))
  - Concert posters, circa 1966-1970; 6 folders (Box 50 (Oversize))
  - Toronto area real estate files, circa 1995-2000; 32 folders (Box 57)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1977-2009; Series V
  Materials in this series consist of videocassettes, audiocassettes, CD-R's, film reels, and audio reels that were either collected by Tom Davis, or which contain content documenting his life and work in comedy.
  Related Materials
  Audiovisual materials related to Saturday Night Live can be found in Series I.
  - Big Star - #1 Record, undated; 1 (Box 51)
  - Superman 50th anniversary, 1988; 1 (Box 51)
  - Master copy photo book, undated; 1 (Box 51)
  - Tom Davis images/Brice, 2008 December 1; 1 (Box 51)
  - Tonight Show (1 of 2), undated; 1 (Box 51)
  - Tonight Show (2 of 2), undated; 1 (Box 51)
  - The Blues Brothers Live at Winterland, 1978 December 31; 1 (Box 51)
  - Grateful Dead Hour #1081 featuring Tom Davis, undated; 1 (Box 51)
  - DTTW Prod - Tom Davis, 2009 June 10; 1 (Box 51)
  - Grateful Dead Hour #1080 featuring Tom Davis, undated; 1 (Box 51)
  - Grateful Dead Hour #1082 featuring Tom Davis, undated; 1 (Box 51)
  - Tom Davis book party, undated; 1 (Box 51)
  - "Hare Krishna Kirtan," Jaya Jagadisha Hari Prayer, undated; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002137181450)
  - "Spinal Tap I", 1984 May 4; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002137181468)
  - "Spinal Tap II", 1984 May 4; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002137181518)
  - Trailer Park #1, 2 Starring Tom Davis, undated; 1 (Box 52, Item barcode 39002137181500)
  - Jacque Tati, undated; 1 (Box 53)
  - "1. Dead - Radio City; 2. The San Francisco Sound; The Complete Beatles", undated; 1 (Box 53)
  - "Tom Davis Voiceover, Artisan 6:30", undated; 1 (Box 53)
  - "Blues Brothers Show Master (Revised), Length 59:33, 5/14/93", 1993 May 14; 1 (Box 53)
  - "Bear City, undated; 1 (Box 53)
  - "NSP-100 Demo", 2003 February 19; 1 (Box 53)
  - "Dippy the Hippie", undated; 1 (Box 53)
  - "An Human Echo; Davis on Franken", 2004 October 4; 1 (Box 53)
  - "Franken & Davis at Stockton State, Early Show w/Visual Read Out", 1982 December 14; 1 (Box 53)
  - "One More Saturday Night Trailer", 1986 April 10; 1 (Box 53)
  - "Al Franken & Tom Davis", 1987 January 8; 1 (Box 54)
  - "White House Opening Career Montage", undated; 1 (Box 54)
  - "Mom & Dad Clip for Letterman", 1984 April 16; 1 (Box 54)
  - "Maureen Steele, 'One More Saturday Night' Original Motion Picture Soundtrack, 1985 May 27; 1 (Box 54)
  - "Franken & Davis, PM Magazine", 1981 March 11; 1 (Box 54)
  - "Franken & Davis at the Guthrie No. 1", 2000 October 23; 1 (Box 54)
  - "Dippy the Hippie", undated; 1 (Box 54)
  - "Dippy 3", undated; 1 (Box 54)
  - Franken and Davis Show, undated; 3 (Box 56)
  - Franken and Davis Show, master, undated; 1 (Box 56)
  - Mexican Drugs, undated; 1 (Box 56)
  - Sample Belgian army, undated; 1 (Box 56)
  - Unidentified audio recording, undated; 1 (Box 56)
  - Unidenfitied films, undated; 2 (Box 56)